Guide to the Selma Chadwick Papers ALBA.311
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Selma Chadwick Papers
1928-1962
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Chadwick, Selma
Silver, Beth
ALBA.311
.75 linear feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 half manuscript box
Selma Ruth Chadwick (1904-1962) was a Polish American nurse. She completed her nursing training at Bellevue Hospital in 1928, served as a nurse in the Republican Medical Services during the Spanish Civil War, and later served as a nurse in the United States Army during World War II, eventually earning the rank of Captain. The Selma Chadwick Papers (dated 1928-1962) documents her nursing education and service as a military nurse during the Spanish Civil War and World War II. Materials in this collection include photographic prints, letters written by Chadwick to family and friends during her service, and administrative documents regarding her nursing education and service. The collection also includes materials related to her funeral, including condolence mail and the funeral guest book.
Scope and Contents
The Selma Chadwick Papers (dated 1928-1962) consist of materials created and collected by Selma Chadwick documenting her nursing education and service as a military nurse with the Republican Medical Services during the Spanish Civil War and with the United States Army during World War II. Materials in this collection include photographic prints, letters written by Chadwick to family and friends during her service, and administrative documents regarding her nursing education and service. In her letters, Chadwick describes the types of illness and injuries she observes, explains her decision to go to Spain, discusses her professional plans following the conclusion of her military services, and shares her impressions of Spain, France, and Germany. The collection also includes materials related to her funeral, including condolence mail and the funeral guest book.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Beth Silver, Chadwick's niece, in May 2019; the accession number associated with this gift is 2019.078.
Biographical Note
Selma Ruth Chadwick (1904-1962) was a Polish American nurse. She completed her nursing training at Bellevue Hospital in 1928, served as a nurse in the Republican Medical Services during the Spanish Civil War, and later served as a nurse in the United States Army during World War II, eventually earning the rank of Captain.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital surrogates of some documents and photographs from this collection were created prior to donation.
Military nursing; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Medical care.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Medical care; Silver, Beth
- American National Red Cross Nurse Pin, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bellevue School of Nursing, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Board of Nurse Examiners, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Syracuse University School of Nursing, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Service Records, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs -- General, 1938-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- Photographs -- US Army Hospitals, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
- Letters, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11-16)
- Letters, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Condolence Mail, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
- Funeral Guest Book, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)